Han Liu

https://hanliuai.github.io

(314) 349-4914

Research Interests

My research focuses on human-AI collaboration. I build AI systems and design novel interactions to assist and teach humans on challenging prediction tasks. My work empower humans with AI by deriving useful explanations from AI and making AI more aligned with humans.

Education

University of Chicago

September 2020 - August 2024

Ph.D. in Computer Science

University of Colorado Boulder

August 2019 - July 2020

Ph.D. in Computer Science (transferred out)

Washington University in St. Louis

August 2015 - May 2019

B.A. in Mathematics, Computer Science, and Minor in Linguistics

Research Experience

University of Chicago, Chicago Human+AI Lab Research Assistant (Advisor: Prof. Chenhao Tan)

September 2020 - Present

Chicago, IL

Project 1: Al-driven Tutorials for Image Classification

- Developed deep learning models integrating task supervision and human perception signals, improving non-expert accuracy by 13-17% with model explanations. [2]
- Designed case-based reasoning interactions, significantly enhancing user decision-making in medical and natural image classification.

Project 2: Prostate Cancer Diagnosis with AI

- Developed models for detecting prostate cancer from MRI scans, securing a top-6 placement in the PICAI challenge.
- Designed user interfaces and conducted cross-institutional studies, demonstrating that AI-assisted diagnosis significantly enhanced accuracy and specificity in prostate cancer detection.

Project 3: Improving Value Alignment of Large Language Models

- Investigated limitations of previous reinforcement learning from human preferences (RLHF) algorithms under conditions of heterogeneous human preference data.
- Extended the direct preference optimization (DPO) algorithm with diverse divergence constraints. [1]

Microsoft Research, Human-AI eXperiences (HAX) Team Research Intern (Manager: Dr. Saleema Amershi)

June 2022 - September 2022 Redmond, WA

- Designed and piloted user studies of code generation models, using multiple human evaluation metrics.
- Analyzed alignment between offline automatic evaluation metrics and human values, informing development and deployment decisions. [3]

University of Colorado Boulder, NLP+CSS Lab

Research Assistant (Advisor: Prof. Chenhao Tan)

August 2019 - August 2020 Boulder, CO

- Studied how human and AI collaborate and complement each other under the effect of distribution shift and interactive interfaces in various decision making tasks such as deceptive review detection, profession classification, and recidivism prediction. [4]
- Analyzed results from large-scale human experiments to study how different types of model-driven tutorials and real-time assistance from model explanations help humans in decision making tasks. [5]

Selected Publications

- [1] Chaoqi Wang, Yibo Jiang, Chenghao Yan, **Han Liu**, and Yuxin Chen. Beyond Reverse KL: Generalizing Direct Preference Optimization with Diverse Divergence Constraints. In *International Conference on Learning Representations*, (ICLR 2024, Spotlight).
- [2] Han Liu, Yizhou Tian, Chacha Chen, Shi Feng, Yuxin Chen, and Chenhao Tan. Learning Human-Compatible Representations for Case-Based Decision Support. In *International Conference on Learning Representations*, (ICLR 2023).
- [3] Victor Dibia, Adam Fourney, Gagan Bansal, Forough Poursabzi-Sangdeh, **Han Liu**, and Saleema Amershi. Aligning Offline Metrics and Human Judgments of Value of AI-Pair Programmers. In Findings of the Association for Computational Linguistics: ACL 2023, (Findings of ACL 2023).
- [4] Han Liu, Vivian Lai, and Chenhao Tan. Understanding the Effect of Out-of-distribution Examples and Interactive Explanations on Human-AI Decision Making. Proceedings of the ACM on Human-Computer Interaction, Volume 5, Issue CSCW2, (CSCW 2021).
- [5] Vivian Lai, **Han Liu**, and Chenhao Tan. "Why is 'Chicago' deceptive?" Towards Building Model-Driven Tutorials for Humans. In *Proceedings of the 2020 CHI Conference on Human Factors in Computing Systems*, (CHI 2020).

More publications can be found on Google Scholar.

Technical Skills

Programming LanguagesPython, Java, C++, SQL, JavaScript, HTML, CSSMachine Learning ToolsPyTorch, Keras, Scikit-learn, Pandas, NumPy, Jupyter

Web Development React, Node.js, Vue.js, jQuery, Django, Bootstrap, MySQL, SQLite

Experience with training and inference with Large Language Models (LLMs) and Vision-Language Models (VLMs): LLaMA-2, Vicuna, LLaVA, CLIP etc.

Teaching Experience

Teaching assistant for the following courses (selected):

CMSC 25100: Introduction to Machine Learning (UChicago, Winter 2024)

CMSC 35400: Machine Learning (UChicago, Sprint 2024) CSCI 5622: Machine Learning (CU Boulder, Fall 2019)

CSE 559A: Computer Vision (WUSTL, Fall 2018)

CSE 511A: Introduction to Artificial Intelligence (WUSTL, Fall 2018)